<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-30T08:12:38+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>I&apos;m a PhD student at Malmö University looking into automatic Game Testing and Quality Assurance. On this blog, I document my research journey. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Last day at Skövde</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last-Day-in-Sk%C3%B6vde/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Last day at Skövde"/><published>2024-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last%20Day%20in%20Sk%C3%B6vde</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last-Day-in-Sk%C3%B6vde/"><![CDATA[<p>Today marks my final workday at the University of Skövde. I have worked here for almost five years, and I believe that a summarization is in order.</p> <h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>The first of January 2020, mere months before the Covid-19 pandemic hit Sweden, my work at the University of Skövde begun after a year and a half at Blekinge Institute of Technology where I worked after my studies. Looking back and reflecting over these years, I realize just how formative they have been. Here, I make an attempt at summarizing the experience I have had over these years.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="courses">Courses</h1> <p>Over the years, I have had the good fortune to work with multiple courses at the university. This work has ranged from taking over courses that has been running smoothly for years to create completely new courses.</p> <h2 id="game-physics">Game Physics</h2> <blockquote> <p>If the students understands why the physics part of the game engine is hard to get right, then they understand the course.</p> </blockquote> <p>One of my first tasks at the University of Skövde was to take over and run the course Game Physics. This course was offered to the third year game programming students and focused on understanding why physics are hard to get right in games – especially if one take into account the need for performance as well. The course was initially developed by Henrik Engström, who was also the examiner for the course, and was only to be given two more times before being phased out from the program. As the course was to be given in the autumn, I had almost half a year to make myself familiar with the content and update it where necessary.</p> <p>This was at the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic and I realized that, come autumn, we risked seeing an upswing in infected again. As I needed to read up on and understand the material anyway, I decided to completely change how the material was to be presented to the students. Instead of holding traditiona two-hours lectures, I divided the material into 16 categories, all but one containing between two and eight short lectures. Each lecture was a video recording, about five minutes long, presenting and explaining a concept relevant for the understanding of game physics. All in all, I recorded just shy of 85 video lectures for this course. As a complement to these video lectures there were weekly seminars for which the students could submit questions or ask for clarifications for concepts they had encountered in the material. Runnable simulations, with code, were also provided for the course. These I worked with translating from the original C++ implementation in a framework created by Prof. Engström to Unity, as this was the environment the students were used to.</p> <p>For assignments I kept the original course assignment as they were – five short group projects and one bigger individual work. The shorter group projects were divided into real-world and simulation assignments. These were to be presented as a video for the real-world assignments or as an executable for the simulation ones. These were shown during a seminar and the students were encouraged to discuss each other’s solutions. Common errors were compiled and presented as extra material for the student group. The indidvidual work ran alongside these group works. Here, the students chose a physic phenomena to simulate and write a report about. To support the students in the report writing, a necessarity due to the lack of training through the programe, a writing guide was compiled and given to the students.</p> <h2 id="game-projects">Game Projects</h2> <hr/> <h1 id="theses">Theses</h1> <hr/> <h1 id="view-on-research">View on Research</h1> <hr/> <h1 id="view-on-pedagogy">View on Pedagogy</h1> <hr/> <h1 id="union-commitment">Union Commitment</h1> <hr/> <h1 id="safety-representative">Safety Representative</h1> <hr/> <h1 id="personal-life">Personal Life</h1> <hr/> <h1 id="finishing-words">Finishing Words</h1>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="University of Skövde"/><category term="Work"/><category term="University of Skövde"/><category term="Teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today marks my final workday at the University of Skövde. I have worked here for almost five years, and I believe that a summarization is in order.]]></summary></entry></feed>