<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-24T13:51:54+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>I&apos;m a PhD student at Malmö University looking into automatic Game Testing and Quality Assurance. On this blog, I document my research journey. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Accepted to FDG’25 Doctoral Consortium</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2025/Accepted-to-FDG'25-Doctoral-Consortium/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Accepted to FDG’25 Doctoral Consortium"/><published>2025-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2025/Accepted%20to%20FDG&apos;25%20Doctoral%20Consortium</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2025/Accepted-to-FDG&apos;25-Doctoral-Consortium/"><![CDATA[<p>The 11th of February, I got an email from the Co-Chairs of the Doctoral Consortium for FDG’25 – I am in!</p> <p>The doctoral consortium for FDG’25 is taking place in Graz, Austria, April 15 - 18. I am honored to have been accepted (with a rating of “strong accept” as recommendation from the anonymous reviewer) to this event, although I will not be able to attend in person<sup id="fnref:personal_reason" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:personal_reason" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Instead, it is my hope that I can attend online this year, as outlined in the information before application is sent in, and apply for another consortium in the not-to-far future where I can be present. Below, you can read my application to the event – should you be interested in what I do.</p> <h1 id="the-paper">The Paper</h1> <object data="https://AndreasJ93.github.io/assets/pdfs/2025_FDGApplication.pdf#view=FitH" width="1000" height="1000" type="application/pdf"></object> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:personal_reason" role="doc-endnote"> <p>I am actually becoming a father for the second time, with expected delivery date the 16th of April, pushed forward from the initial 11th <a href="#fnref:personal_reason" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The 11th of February, I got an email from the Co-Chairs of the Doctoral Consortium for FDG’25 – I am in!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paper for the Doctoral Course Research in Collaboration</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2025/Paper-for-Doctoral-Course-Research-in-Collaboration/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper for the Doctoral Course Research in Collaboration"/><published>2025-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2025/Paper%20for%20Doctoral%20Course%20Research%20in%20Collaboration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2025/Paper-for-Doctoral-Course-Research-in-Collaboration/"><![CDATA[<p>A course I am really happy to have been part of this year was the course “Research in Collaboration: theories, methods, practices and ethics”. This course have not only presented me with tools to tackle what I believe is a problem with games research, but also given me an arena to reflect over my practice. Interested? Keep reading for more info!</p> <p>Collaborative research has through the course been used as an umbrella term for research conducted in collaboration with non-academic stakeholders. Reading through courses I could take at Malmö University, that was precisely what caught my eyes – the prospect of methodologies and practices in engaging and working with non-academics for a shared research endevor. My experience with games research, at least when it comes to “games for entertainment”, is that a lot is done within the walls of academia and rarely becomes useful for practitioners in the games industry.</p> <p>Throughout the course I was presented with differentiating views and ideas regarding collaborative research. While almost all of these discussed big problems in the world like social injustices, healthcare, citizen participation, and enviromental issues, I felt that these methods could be used and extrapolated upon. So for the essay of the course, I wrote about the gap between game development and games research and how, given the chance, <em>Collaborative Research</em> could introduce new ways of conducting research within the field.</p> <p>Want to understand what I mean? Please, do read the paper below!</p> <h1 id="the-paper">The Paper</h1> <object data="https://AndreasJ93.github.io/assets/pdfs/2024_MAU0004.pdf#view=FitH" width="1000" height="1000" type="application/pdf"></object>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A course I am really happy to have been part of this year was the course “Research in Collaboration: theories, methods, practices and ethics”. This course have not only presented me with tools to tackle what I believe is a problem with games research, but also given me an arena to reflect over my practice. Interested? Keep reading for more info!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Paper for the SSFR Doctoral Course</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Paper-for-the-SSFR-Doctoral-Course/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Paper for the SSFR Doctoral Course"/><published>2024-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Paper%20for%20the%20SSFR%20Doctoral%20Course</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Paper-for-the-SSFR-Doctoral-Course/"><![CDATA[<p>This January I am presenting a Positional Paper as part of the Doctoral course arranged by <a href="https://spelforskarradet.se/en/start-english/">Svenska Spelforskarrådet</a> (Council of Swedish Games Researchers). Want to read it? See the end of this post! </p> <p>In many ways, this positional paper is the first time I have written anything ‘‘formal’’ regarding my thoughts and views on research – in particular Game Research. It is an area I know contains many facets and differentiating opinions, and I feel like the paper I wrote contains a few points that I would have wanted to do more research around had this been for a conference or to be published more formally.</p> <p>I do, however, believe that the paper touches upon one of the erroneous ways game research today is conducted within academia; the lack of understanding of the development context. Few projects, regardless of focus seems to be done within the actual constraints of a game development company. It does not matter if the constraints are financial ones or, as for instance in the area of Game AI, computational time allowed and fidelity required – I rarely see these kept in mind as the research is conducted. This, in my humble opinion, causes a rift between academia and industry, wherein the produce and knowledge generation of the former are all but useless for the later.</p> <p>Want to understand what I mean? Please, do read the paper below!</p> <h1 id="the-paper">The Paper</h1> <object data="https://AndreasJ93.github.io/assets/pdfs/2024_SSFR.pdf#view=FitH" width="1000" height="1000" type="application/pdf"></object>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This January I am presenting a Positional Paper as part of the Doctoral course arranged by Svenska Spelforskarrådet (Council of Swedish Games Researchers). Want to read it? See the end of this post!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Presentation from the Start-Up Seminar</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Presentation-from-the-Start-Up-Seminar/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Presentation from the Start-Up Seminar"/><published>2024-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Presentation%20from%20the%20Start-Up%20Seminar</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Presentation-from-the-Start-Up-Seminar/"><![CDATA[<p>The 17th of January I presented at my Start-Up Seminar. In this post, you can not only read my thoughts about the seminar, but also the presentation itself. </p> <p>The presentation was conducted in a small room at Malmö University with an audience consisting of my three supervisors, my examiner, and a few members of the faculty that were interested in hearing my plans for the research project. Most importantly for me, both my wife and son were present; giving me a well-needed boost of confidence. Through Zoom, members of the Game Tech Academy project were welcomed to join.</p> <p>The presentation went smoothly and I managed to hold the time without any hitches. After some feedback and questions from my examiner – which I do hope I managed to answer in a satisfying manner – the floor was opened for the faculty.</p> <p>All in all, I believe that I gave a proper view of my plans going forth and managed to clear out any questions. With my ISP (individual study plan) approved, it is time to start properly working on this research!</p> <h1 id="presentation">Presentation</h1> <object data="https://AndreasJ93.github.io/assets/pdfs/2024_StartUp.pdf#view=Fit" width="1000" height="1000" type="application/pdf"></object>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The 17th of January I presented at my Start-Up Seminar. In this post, you can not only read my thoughts about the seminar, but also the presentation itself.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Start-Up Seminar Schdeuled</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Start-Up-Seminar-Scheduled/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Start-Up Seminar Schdeuled"/><published>2024-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Start-Up%20Seminar%20Scheduled</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Start-Up-Seminar-Scheduled/"><![CDATA[<p>The start-up seminar for my PhD, where I will present my planned research for the faculty, has been scheduled to December 17th. More information inside the post! During this seminar, the faculty will be able to give me peer feedback and engage in discussions around, or criticise, my planned work. It is all done so that I can give my plans another thought with a focus on an outside view which may otherwise be hard to get. After the seminar, I will have my first ISP review with my examiner. Should the seminar be open for the public, a link for a Zoom-meeting will also be provided here at a later date.</p> <p><strong>Title</strong> Leveling Up the Indie Scene: Automatic Play Testing and Quality Assurance</p> <p><strong>Abstract</strong> An important, yet difficult and often overlooked, part of any game development endeavour is testing. From game play testing, wherein you ensure that your players react the way you expect to your product, to quality assurance, wherein you ensure that the game work and behaves as expected, testing is important to ensure that the finished product is up to par. Within the AAA games industry, automatic testing is under development and an active point of in-house research. Mainly done by either hard-coded agents in the game or different machine learning technologies that requires a lot of gameplay data and resources to train, these technologies can be hard to reuse by other actors in the game development space. How can the findings from the AAA developers be leveraged for development of technologies suitable for small-scale developers like the indie and hobbyist scene that dominates the Nordic game development scene? As a doctoral student within the project Game Tech Academy, that is what I have set out to uncover.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The start-up seminar for my PhD, where I will present my planned research for the faculty, has been scheduled to December 17th. More information inside the post!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">AI and Games Conference</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/AI-and-Games-Conference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI and Games Conference"/><published>2024-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/AI%20and%20Games%20Conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/AI-and-Games-Conference/"><![CDATA[<p>As I am writing this, I am currently on the flight back from the <a href="https://www.aiandgamesconference.com/">AI and Games Conference 2024</a> in London. The first of, hopefully, many!</p> <p>At this venue, I had the great fortune to talk with people from both academia and industry, make valuable connections and, perhaps most importantly, get an insight into what is going on in the industry.</p> <p>The <a href="https://www.aiandgamesconference.com/">AI and Games Conference 2024</a> was a first in many ways, shapes, and forms. It was the first time this conference was arranged, it was my first international conference, my first time in London (and the UK at large), <em>and</em> it was my first international travel without my wife. That’s actually where I am going to start this blog post, with my wife.</p> <h1 id="my-wife">My Wife</h1> <p>My wife is the love of my life. Right now, as I am working on my PhD – fulfilling my dream – she is at home with our 14 months old son, taking care of him. Every week when I travel to Malmö, she handles our son and takes care of everything at home. And the days I am home in Skövde, this incredible woman <em>goes to work</em> to help making sure that we have the economy to push through this. Oh, and did I mention that she is also four months pregnant, as we are expecting our <em>second</em> child. I feel like, and I think this is the proper English term for it, like a proper twat for pursuing my PhD at this time. All this woman does through thick and thin is to give me her unyielding support, especially emotionally as I am a wreck at times. I love her to death, and I really have to step up my husband game for life for this. My love, if you read this, I will be better at letting my action speak for my love and not my words – something I am currently <em>very</em> bad at!</p> <h1 id="the-beginning">The Beginning</h1> <p>So, short story first. When Tommy Thompson <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xj9lWvaBRUg&amp;ab_channel=AIandGames">announced the AI and Games Conference</a> (August 16), I had more or less just been accepted to my PhD position at Malmö University. I emailed José, my main supervisor, on the spot, asking for the possibility to secure a ticket seeing that it all sounded <em>highly</em> relevant for my PhD. He agreed of the relevance, and quickly helped me fix all the bureaucracy around the ticket. About two weeks later, I had secured my ticket to the event, and one of the first things I did after having formally started my PhD position was to fix tickets for the airport and book a Hostel. Now, back to the main story.</p> <h1 id="pre-conference">Pre-Conference</h1> <p>My trip to London was – all in all – uneventful. I left home early (the Swedish railways are not always reliable, and I did not want to miss my flight), arriving at Arlanda about four hours before my flight. Getting caught up in the security screening (as I almost always do), I finally made it to the waiting area. After some work and food, I boarded my flight, flew over that little pond of water, and arrived at a stereotypical cloudy and foggy London Gatwick Airport. With some help from the railway station personnel, I got on the right train to London Bridge. At London Bridge, I changed to New Cross and made my way to the Hostel where I was staying (quite the rundown place in a few ways, but it was cheap). Having checked in, I made my way over the street to a local pub where – perfectly planned by Aji, one of the community members of the AI and Games channel and a lovely fellow swede – an informal pre-conference meetup was taking place. During this meetup, I got to talk with a lot of interesting people, but most important for my story are Aji and Liam. Remember Liam, he will be very important later!</p> <p>After a night of okay sleep (sharing room with 5 others + a busy street with emergency services all the time) I took a cold shower (probably my own non-understanding of the concept of British showers, but there were only one knob!) and went hunting for food. I found a nice little coffee place just down the street, got some coffee and a sandwich, and was at the AI and Game Conference venue well in time for the conference.</p> <h1 id="at-the-conference">At the Conference</h1> <p>From the get-go, I felt at home at this conference. I exchanged a few words with the – as I have understood it afterwards – main on-site whirlwind of getting-everything-up-and-ready, Sally Kevan – an absolutely lovely person that had so much energy around her. As the conference had sold out, it was a lot of badges to sort and people to accommodate at the venue. Sally, on the off chance that you are reading this: fantastic work! I met up with a few of the people from yesterday, exchanged some words and pleasantries, and then went our separate ways for the first talk. As Tommy welcomed everyone – streamed into the room I sat in – it finally clicked; I was actually here.</p> <p>The next hours were an onslaught of information, new ideas, and discussions. A proper smörgåsbord, if you will. I had the good fortune to listen to:</p> <ul> <li>Arya Subramanyam from Amazon Web Services, giving a strong talk regarding <em>Harnessing Multi-Agent Systems for Task Execution</em>, a talk that gave me a lot of new ideas in how to look at handling the complexity I will most likely meet during my studies, <p> </p> </li> <li>Monica Villanueva Aylagas from EA Seed gave the talk <em>Avalon: Can we Improve the Validity of Match-3 Games Level Generation</em>, which gave me an entire new view of how the information from a testing suit can be presented, and that we can introduce constraints to help guiding the system to create valid content, <p> </p> </li> <li>– Break, talked to a lot of people, got to know a few of them better, and shared stories and interesting anecdotes, <p> </p> </li> <li>Anna Poulter-Jones from Sheridans gave a talk regarding <em>Navigating AI and IP: A Practical Toolkit for Devs</em> which, even if perhaps not directly related as of now, gave me information I will most likely have to seek out soon anyway, <p> </p> </li> <li>Raluca Gaina and Diego Perez from Tabletop R&amp;D gave one of the most relevant talks for me, <em>Empowering Game Designers with Automatic Playtesting</em> showcasing their own work with tabletop games and giving me a <em>ton</em> of ideas for my own PhD studies and how to look forward, <p> </p> </li> <li>Brendan Mulcahy from Epic Games discussed the experimental framework <em>Learning Agents in Unreal Engine</em>, giving a few insights in how one of the industry giants are working with related technologies for their Player-Bots, <p> </p> </li> <li>Alessandro Sestini and Luca Ballore from Electronic Arts and Electronic Arts Seed respectively discussed <em>AgentMerge: Enhancing Battlefield Automated Issue Management with LLMs</em>, giving a rare insight in how an repetitive and non-intuitive part of the QA pipeline and debugging work could be assisted with tools driven by LLMs, with only a 4 % false positive rate and a ticket handling speedup of nearly 3x, <p> </p> </li> <li>– Lunch, and a lot of discussion with many people; both presenters and attendees. Liam, my saviour, supported me and helped looking out for my bag as I was running around like a headless chicken, <p> </p> </li> <li>Sam Devlin from Microsoft Research turned it all on its head, as he presented the process for the AI when they’re <em>Learning to Play, Imitate, and Collaborate with Pesky Humans: Some Lessons from the AI’s Perspective</em>, an interesting talk giving me great insights! <p> </p> </li> <li>Jaden Travnik from Sony AI probably held the presentation I felt most influential, as he made the case that <em>RL Agent Training is Property Based Training</em>. Deriving from this presentation, and piecing together bits and pieces from all the talks I attended, I think I have a better idea of how automatic Playtesting and automatic Quality Assurance can co-exist and help each other out, at least to a degree <p> </p> </li> <li>Following this was a panel with representatives from Amazon Web Services (Andrei Muratov), Unity Technologies (Changed from the program, I forgot your name, sorry!), Arm (Roberto Lopez Mendez), and Kinetix (Yassine Tahi). Hearing they talk and discuss <em>The Future of AI for Games</em> was a treat!, <p> </p> </li> <li>– Afternoon break, more talks and discussions with presenters and new friends alike!, <p> </p> </li> <li>Laurent Couvidou from Build a Rocket Boy gave the only “back to basic” AI agent talk I attended: <em>Tethering Agents for the Greater Good</em>, a great talk regarding keeping agents in specific areas without the player noticing all too much, and how this was implemented in different games he had worked with, <p> </p> </li> <li>Christoph Salge from the University of Hertfordshire talked about ten years of <em>The AI Settlement Generation Challenge in Minecraft</em>, a competition I think I have to get into at some point!, <p> </p> </li> <li>Lastly, the event was for me ended with Eric Jacopin from Hawkswell, talking about how <em>Analytic Geometry is your Friend</em>, a heavy and well conducted talk my head was <em>not</em> ready for. I really must get back and look at the recording for this once it is up! <p> </p> </li> </ul> <p>Unfortunately, I could not attend the Closing Remark by Tommy, instead opting to call home and say goodnight to my wife and kid. But what a venue! It was a lovely experience all around, and I just loved every second of it!</p> <h2 id="going-forward">Going Forward</h2> <p>A quick note here regarding the impact this event had on how I see my studies going forward. As I have just started working on my PhD, I feel like I am easily influenced and wish to explore so many venues, nooks, and crannies. However, after these talks, I think I am starting to see a pattern regarding the usage of AI techniques, training, data, and game code. There are a lot to bone out still, and I will most likely contact all of the people in the above list and try to prick their brains a bit in the following months – after I have done some reading and gotten all of the PhD position formalities out of the way. I took a <em>lot</em> of notes, and I will make sure to rewatch a few of these talks for a few key points I think I heard, but I think I have an idea regarding how to playtest in a more general capability – maybe.</p> <p>I have five years to figure this out, right?</p> <h1 id="post-conference">Post-Conference</h1> <p>Now, remember Liam from earlier? If not, he is this cool dude, a junior programmer, that have been an absolute delight to hang out with. For my visit, he was important for this next part.</p> <p>As the conference came to an end, I had a dilemma. As I mentioned earlier, I stayed at New Cross, at a place that got a few of the attendees raise an eyebrow. The area did not feel particularly safe, and with the after-conference reception being half-an-hour walk away, and the fact that I was discouraged by a few people from taking a cab that late, I would either have to re-accommodate or skip the reception. After having discussed it with my wife, she said I should go for it and re-accommodate – making sure I took all opportunities I could as I was away. Said and done! Teary eyed (remember that emotional support from earlier? Yeah, she does not know half of it…), I saw the people swarming out from the wrap-up and caught Liam – the hobbit (his own words, not mine). I explained the situation to him, and he was happy to follow me back to the hostel, check out, and guided me and Aji to the reception – keeping us safe in the weirdness that is London. Liam “Sam” Snow may not sound the hero I paint him up to be here, but there and then I was eternally grateful for having this hobbit (once again, his words not mine) with me!</p> <p>At the reception it was a lot of mingling about, getting to know people in a more relaxed environment. Here, I remembered that I had brought with me my business cards (as one do) and started handing them out to people I had talked with during the event and presenters. As the night progressed I went between the table where Aji and Liam had parked and around the reception, anchored (or tethered) to the safety of Aji and Liam. During the reception, I also booked a room and checked into the hotel, feeling safe and warm.</p> <p>As the night progressed, I realized that there was a person that I had yet to speak with; Tommy himself. I have long been a fan of his work, often using it as a starting point when it comes to my own curiosity and as one of my most recommended ways to understand AI for my students – often linking to his channel in different courses. Where Julian has been a research hero for many years, Tommy has been a true inspiration when it comes to brining academia and industry together – highlighting how the symbiotic relationship can work. As he said himself as the night progressed; this conference was 80 % industry, 20 % academia. In fact, I have Tommy to thank for my understanding of AI from “the other side”, giving me invaluable tools when dwelling deeper into research and industry discussions. I would have been amiss if I did not speak to him, but I really did not want to bother him – I always feel a bit too much in the way on these events!</p> <p>Towards what I thought would be the end of the night, I finally got to exchange a few words with Tommy, thanking him for the event and introducing myself. However, the night had a few other plans. I joined Tommy and a few of the organisers and attendees for a late dinner, a pub visit, a long talk in the hotel bar (not leaving before 2 in the morning). It was just a great ending, one I could not have hoped for, to a long conference day – sharing laughs, a beer or two, and stories with these lovely people – in a way that just felt natural.</p> <p>The day after, I sat down and had breakfast with a few of the organisers and attendees again. I heard background stories about the conference, how things shaped up, and thoughts about the possibilities at large. As I left the group to prepare for check-out and making my way to the train station, I felt like I left something great behind. But I also felt extremely welcomed and embraced by this community, regardless of whom I spoke with.</p> <h1 id="the-trip-home">The trip home</h1> <p>Now, the trip home was not the best I have done. As I enjoyed my time at breakfast, I kept a close look on my watch – knowing that the trip from the hotel to the airport would take about an hour, I set out to be two hours early for my flight. What I did not know was that the trains did <em>not</em> go from London Bridge to Gatewick (despite the lovely lady at Greenwhich station saying they did). So… I panicked. A lot. Luckily, the informant at London Bridge helped me plan a route, I was able to check in to my flight online, and I ended up being cleared through security about an hour before departure. I do hope my writings in the conference social channel brought a few smiles at least. Quoting myself as the panic released it grip on me:</p> <blockquote> <p>I just realized that this chat quickly turned into “Swedish man panicking overseas, bringing shame to his Viking heritage”, so I do hope you enjoyed that!</p> </blockquote> <p>As I am writing this, I am on the last ledge on my journey; on a train between Stockholm and Skövde. I am coming home tired, filled with ideas, and just feeling content. As I come home, I am going to take a shower, hold my wife close, and just let this all sink in.</p> <p>One thing is for certain, I am looking forward to see you all at the next AI and Games Conference, or, if you are going to it, the <a href="https://school.gameaibook.org/">International Summer School on AI and Games</a> in Malmö, Sweden, next summer!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><category term="AI and Games"/><category term="Conference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As I am writing this, I am currently on the flight back from the AI and Games Conference 2024 in London. The first of, hopefully, many! At this venue, I had the great fortune to talk with people from both academia and industry, make valuable connections and, perhaps most importantly, get an insight into what is going on in the industry.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sweden Game Conference 2024</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Sweden-Game-Conference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sweden Game Conference 2024"/><published>2024-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Sweden%20Game%20Conference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Sweden-Game-Conference/"><![CDATA[<p>Last week, I attended Sweden Game Conference 2024. It was not my first time, neither do I believe it was my last. Here, I have collected my thoughts and experiences.</p> <p><a href="https://swedengameconference.se/en/">Sweden Game Conference</a> is held yearly in Skövde, Sweden. It is a conference aimed at the industry, with a close connection to <a href="https://his.se/en">University of Skövde</a> and the <a href="https://skovde.se">Skövde Municipality</a>, with talks, panels, pitch events, and more. For the students at the University of Skövde, there are also the opportunity to win the <a href="https://skovde.se/naringsliv-arbete/Naringslivet-i-Skovde/skovde-academic-game-award/">SAGA award</a>. For teachers and educators in Game Development, the <a href="https://spelforskarradet.se/en/start-english/">Council of Swedish Game Researchers</a>(Svenska Spelforskarrådet) hosts the Game Educator Summit.</p> <p>During my time at the University of Skövde, especially while course responsible for the Game Project courses, this conference was one I regularly attended. It was a great way to meet students, both current and former, engage in the local and national game development community, as well as to keep oneself updated with the current topics of the game industry – all without leaving Skövde! I have attended every Game Educator Summit – even presented on the topic of Generative AI last year – since its incarnation in 2021. 2021 was also the year I attended the conference for the first time.</p> <p>This year I got to see the conference through other eyes. The key note, A roadmap to the AI revolution in games, made me feel like the area of my PhD was one filled with possibilities. That the key note was held by one of my personal research heroes, <a href="https://engineering.nyu.edu/faculty/julian-togelius">Julian Togelius</a> (currently a guest professor at University of Skövde), <em>and</em> that I had the great pleasure of not only discussing my PhD plans with him over lunch but also take a stroll and discuss a potential project, enhanced the feeling. Following these discussions, I see new possible paths for how to develop this PhD – which I will discuss with my supervisors tomorrow.</p> <p>During the conference I also attended some great talks – many of which gave me new ideas or insights in how tools and systems are actually used by the developers. Jonathan Smårs from Iron Gate, creators of Valheim, talked about the PCG system that build the world for this game, as well as how to use just the right amount of tools (and how to know what tools to develop for others to use). Arvi Teikari, creator of Baba is You, talked about the development of the formentioned game – including both design and buisness decisions. Filippa Arvidsson from Stunlock Studios, most recently known for V Rising, presented the importance of tools for small teams – a talk that really put a perspective on how the slightest change can be of importance. Lastly, I attended the panel regarding automatic tools – hosted by the always amazing Dennis Karugu – which gave me an insight in challenges lying ahead.</p> <p>As tradition holds, the last thing on the agenda was SUP (SpelUtvecklar Pub, GameDeveloper Pub). A few beers and reconnecting with students and game developers in a more laid-back environment – what more could one ask for?</p> <p>Last, but not least, this year’s conference also had a very special event; the unveiling of Skövde’s Walk of Games. While I was unable to attend the unveiling myself, I have since walked the street and looked at the plaques celebrating the biggest releases out of Skövde. If you wish to read more about the Walk of Games, David Hollingsworth at ESTNN made an article that you can read <a href="https://estnn.com/skovde-walk-of-game-a-small-city-with-big-idea/">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><category term="SGC"/><category term="Sweden Game Conference"/><category term="Conference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Last week, I attended Sweden Game Conference 2024. It was not my first time, neither do I believe it was my last. Here, I have collected my thoughts and experiences.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Week as a PhD student</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/A-Week-as-a-PhD/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Week as a PhD student"/><published>2024-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/A%20Week%20as%20a%20PhD</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/A-Week-as-a-PhD/"><![CDATA[<p>I have now been a PhD student for a week. Here are my first thoughts about this journey.</p> <p>The week started as per usual with a new job environment: Orientation. As this is my third time working for a Swedish agency, the previous two having been Blekinge Institute of Technology and University of Skövde, it was not a lot of new information regarding the inner workings of an agency and what to have in mind. Instead, I could focus on listening to the information regarding the internal workings of MAU, the faculty, and the department. This orientation also gave me the opportunity to get to know new colleagues and one of my two co-supervisors, Raquel Robinson – at the time of meeting her, I was not aware that she would be my co-supervisor, but I am happy that she is!</p> <p>As the week progressed I had a long – and uplifting – meeting with my three supervisors; José María Font Fernández as main supervisor and Alberto Alvarez Uribe and Raquel Robinson as co-supervisors. I got an introduction to the project <a href="https://gametechacademy.dk/">Game Tech Academy</a> that I will be a part of, information regarding what is expected of me during these few first months, and a few tasks to work with until our next meeting. This was completed in the afternoon with a meeting by the faculty, where I meet with the Deputy Head of Department, who is responsible for research and research education, and discussed more formal requirements of the PhD. All in all a very informative day with a lot of information.</p> <p>Wednesday I had a meeting with the Head of the Department regarding my institute hours; that is to say, the teaching work expected from me. I start tomorrow, Monday 9<sup>th</sup> of September, with labs in the C# course given to game programming students.</p> <p>After this, it was mostly work as usual. As I had not received my work copmuter yet, I spent my time in the library reading up on the course I was to be teaching in, as well as went through articles I had since earlier to see which could be of use. Friday afternoon I went home to my wife and kid to spend the weekend close to them. All in all, I am looking forward to this journey – even though I am not particullarly fond of the commutes.</p> <p><strong>Bonus</strong> Currently, I am living with a friend I studied with at BTH. Evenings are spent playing some Magic: The Gathering (commander). The four deck I brought with me last week were:</p> <ul> <li>Enchamntment F-You, a deck where I play weird effects on enchantments to twist the rules of the games</li> <li>Legendary Tribal, a deck with legendaries and legendary synergies</li> <li>Artifcat Sacrificial, a deck where I use artifacts with sac-abilities to win</li> <li>Phyrexian Tribal, a deck with the idea of being phyrexians attacking a new plane</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Studies"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have now been a PhD student for a week. Here are my first thoughts about this journey.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Last day at Skövde</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last-Day-in-Sk%C3%B6vde/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Last day at Skövde"/><published>2024-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last%20Day%20in%20Sk%C3%B6vde</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last-Day-in-Sk%C3%B6vde/"><![CDATA[<p>Today marks my final workday at the University of Skövde. I have worked here for almost five years, and I believe that a summarization is in order.</p> <h1 id="introduction">Introduction</h1> <p>On the first of January 2020, mere months before the Covid-19 pandemic hit Sweden, my work at the University of Skövde began after a year and a half at Blekinge Institute of Technology, where I worked after my studies. Looking back and reflecting over these years, I realize just how formative they have been. Here, I make an attempt at summarizing the experience I have had over these years.</p> <hr/> <ul id="markdown-toc"> <li><a href="#introduction" id="markdown-toc-introduction">Introduction</a></li> <li><a href="#courses" id="markdown-toc-courses">Courses</a> <ul> <li><a href="#game-physics" id="markdown-toc-game-physics">Game Physics</a></li> <li><a href="#game-projects" id="markdown-toc-game-projects">Game Projects</a></li> <li><a href="#theses" id="markdown-toc-theses">Theses</a></li> </ul> </li> <li><a href="#view-on-research" id="markdown-toc-view-on-research">View on Research</a></li> <li><a href="#view-on-pedagogy" id="markdown-toc-view-on-pedagogy">View on Pedagogy</a></li> <li><a href="#union-commitment" id="markdown-toc-union-commitment">Union Commitment</a></li> <li><a href="#safety-representative" id="markdown-toc-safety-representative">Safety Representative</a></li> <li><a href="#personal-life" id="markdown-toc-personal-life">Personal Life</a></li> <li><a href="#finishing-words" id="markdown-toc-finishing-words">Finishing Words</a></li> </ul> <h1 id="courses">Courses</h1> <p>Over the years, I have had the good fortune to work with multiple courses at the university. This work has ranged from taking over courses that have been running smoothly for years to creating completely new courses.</p> <h2 id="game-physics">Game Physics</h2> <p>One of my first tasks at the University of Skövde was to take over and run the course Game Physics. This course was offered to the third-year game programming students and focused on understanding why physics is hard to get right in games – especially if one takes into account the need for performance as well. The course was initially developed by Henrik Engström, who was also the examiner for the course, and was only to be given two more times before being phased out from the program. As the course was to be given in the autumn, I had almost half a year to make myself familiar with the content and update it where necessary.This was at the beginning of the Covid-19 pandemic, and I realized that, come autumn, we risked seeing an upswing in infections again. As I needed to read up on and understand the material anyway, I decided to completely change how the material was to be presented to the students. Instead of holding traditional two-hour lectures, I divided the material into 16 categories, all but one containing between two and eight short lectures. Each lecture was a video recording, about five minutes long, presenting and explaining a concept relevant for the understanding of game physics. All in all, I recorded just shy of 85 video lectures for this course. As a complement to these video lectures, there were weekly seminars for which the students could submit questions or ask for clarifications on concepts they had encountered in the material. Runnable simulations, with code, were also provided for the course. These I worked with translating from the original C++ implementation in a framework created by Prof. Engström to Unity, as this was the environment the students were used to.For assignments, I kept the original course assignments as they were – five short group projects and one bigger individual work. The shorter group projects were divided into real-world and simulation assignments. These were to be presented as a video for the real-world assignments or as an executable for the simulation ones. These were shown during a seminar, and the students were encouraged to discuss each other’s solutions. Common errors were compiled and presented as extra material for the student group. The individual work ran alongside these group works. Here, the students chose a physics phenomenon to simulate and write a report about. To support the students in the report writing, a necessity due to the lack of training through the programme, a writing guide was compiled and given to the students.</p> <h2 id="game-projects">Game Projects</h2> <p>During my first year at Skövde, one of my colleagues left for a job within QA at Paradox Interactive. Being relatively free with a lot of hours to find work for, I was thrown into the world of Game Project courses as course responsible together with another colleague. While Skövde has had game project courses since the programs started, this was an entirely new iteration of courses. More importantly, there were now three of them. As I worked with my colleague to understand this course, I also realized that the following two courses were not even in development yet. As such, I proposed to change that and took a holistic approach to creating the courses Game Project 2 and Game Project 3. At the same time, my colleague and I changed a lot of the core in Game Project 1 based on our own and students’ reflections.This work was very rewarding, but also very draining. It started with gathering information, allowing me as an outsider to finally get a glimpse of not only the history of game development that exists in Skövde, but also interviewing and listening in to staff at the department and former students. I conducted interviews, tried to understand how my colleagues saw these courses – whether they had worked in them or not was irrelevant. I listened to the professionals from the industry around us, and read through research regarding game project courses around the world, transdisciplinary courses around the world, as well as game development reports and books. With all this in mind, I started compiling rough drafts for the two courses, using two colleagues for discussions, and presented them to the programme co-ordinators. After taking their responses and compiling them, tweaking the courses, I presented them to the department before they were adopted.I knew that these courses would not be entirely what students, or colleagues, expected. My aim was to give students the tools to succeed in the industry, to differentiate themselves from the students that had passed a higher vocational education programme. What I got was a… reputation. I hope to one day be able to sit down and present each of the Game Project courses in exhaustive detail; focusing on the development of the courses, the challenges they faced, and how the students reacted. However, that day is not today.</p> <hr/> <h2 id="theses">Theses</h2> <p>During my time at the University of Skövde, I supervised and examined quite a few theses. Over the years, I have met many different kinds of students and works. I have learned a lot from both supervising and examining these works – and even if I might have a higher standard than expected at times, I believe that most students have enjoyed the time as well. There’s something special about seeing the student’s academic prowess bloom like you do as a supervisor and examiner, how you must follow their thought process on the paper, and can guide them towards clarity and brevity with their texts. At times, I have been harsh with my comments or feedback – but at the end of the day, all I want is for my students to finish their studies having learned what they need to learn.For a list of all theses I supervised and examined during my time at the University of Skövde, <a href="/teaching/Theses_HiS">see this page</a>.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="view-on-research">View on Research</h1> <p>One thing that really changed during my time at the University of Skövde was how I view research. When I arrived at the university, I came from an engineering background with a high emphasis on measurable – quantitative – data for research. I cannot even say that I looked down on qualitative research – that would be to give myself way too much credit. No, the truth is that I almost completely dismissed research that was not of the sound, measurable, statistically provable kind. After a stern talk with – more a lecture given by – professor Henrik Engström, I slowly opened up my mind to the idea of something more. Sidenote: On the topic of Prof. Henrik Engström, I warmly recommend his book Game Development Research, which can be found <a href="https://gamedevresearch.se/">here</a></p> <p>That was a rabbit hole, as this not only opened my eyes to qualitative research, but also to the idea of inter- and transdisciplinary research. This new perspective made me spend hours searching for research for the game project courses, but also helped me as I looked into research that could be suitable for other courses in the Game Programming programme that I was a teacher in. It has given me countless new perspectives and helped me develop myself both professionally and personally. Most importantly for my time at Skövde, and for my journey ahead, it has given me new perspectives on games, game testing, and game development at large.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="view-on-pedagogy">View on Pedagogy</h1> <p>During my time at the University of Skövde, I was required – as part of my contract – to complete 15 credits worth of pedagogy courses. These courses have shaped my pedagogy in many ways, and also opened up new keywords to use when searching for research for my courses. Most importantly, however, it gave me time to reflect on my ideas and ideals, my pedagogy, and what I believe is important for learning.Interestingly enough, the end result is mainly not a shift in my pedagogical beliefs, but rather an understanding regarding how I can support students more effectively in their learning. For me, the most important part is that the students are here by their own free will, wishing to learn. This, for me, means two things. Firstly, my work is therefore to give the students the best education I can offer. Secondly, and most importantly, it means that the students have to take responsibility for their studies and not expect to be spoon-fed everything. With this in mind, my aim is always to have courses with clear goals, a thought-out progress, being open-minded and listening to the students, and challenging them in ways aimed to deepen their knowledge – not only during assessments, but also through the material and communication.Of course, there is a lot more to it than this. As part of a later course I took at Skövde, I started writing down my Pedagogical Philosophy. In the future, I plan to revisit this document and upload it here. For now, this short text will suffice.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="union-commitment">Union Commitment</h1> <p>During my time at Skövde, I also had some commitment to <a href="https://sulf.se/en/">SULF</a>, The Swedish Association of University Teachers and Researchers. I was a union representative for the local union for two years. However, this is not something I wish to highlight too much; in truth, I did little more than join meetings and help arrange minor activities for our members.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="safety-representative">Safety Representative</h1> <p>A role I was more involved in, however, was as a safety representative. Most of it I’m not allowed to talk about due to the duty of confidentiality that is part of the role. What I can say is that I played an active role in developing new ways for HR and safety representatives to cooperate for a better work environment.</p> <hr/> <h1 id="personal-life">Personal Life</h1> <p>I would be remiss if I didn’t cover some of the important parts that happened to me personally during my time at Skövde. So here it comes, in chronological order:</p> <ul> <li>My significant other and I took the trip we always dreamed about to Osaka, Japan</li> <li>I turned 30, which I have heard is some kind of milestone</li> <li>I got married to the love of my life</li> <li>My son, Andrej, was born</li> </ul> <hr/> <h1 id="finishing-words">Finishing Words</h1> <p>My time at Skövde has been wonderful, and there are many – students, colleagues, and peers from the local game development scene – that I’ll miss meeting on a regular basis. Many of them I’ll meet and talk with as part of the PhD project; others I’ll certainly run into during my stays in Skövde.But now, forward to new adventures. Allons-y!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="University of Skövde"/><category term="Work"/><category term="University of Skövde"/><category term="Teaching"/><category term="Reflections"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today marks my final workday at the University of Skövde. I have worked here for almost five years, and I believe that a summarization is in order.]]></summary></entry></feed>