<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-08-30T07:07:18+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>I&apos;m a PhD student at Malmö University looking into automatic Game Testing and Quality Assurance. On this blog, I document my research journey. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">My Last day at Skövde</title><link href="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last-Day-in-Sk%C3%B6vde/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Last day at Skövde"/><published>2024-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-08-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last%20Day%20in%20Sk%C3%B6vde</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://andreasj93.github.io/blog/2024/Last-Day-in-Sk%C3%B6vde/"><![CDATA[<p>Today marks my final workday at the University of Skövde. I have worked here for almost five years, and I believe that a summarization is in order.</p> <p>#Introduction The first of January 2020, mere months before the Covid-19 pandemic hit Sweden, my work at the University of Skövde begun after a year and a half at Blekinge Institute of Technology where I worked after my studies. Looking back and reflecting over these years, I realize just how formative they have been. Here, I make an attempt at summarizing the experience I have had over these years.</p> <p>#Courses Over the years, I have had the good fortune to work with multiple courses at the university. This work has ranged from taking over courses that has been running smoothly for years to create completely new courses.</p> <p>##Game Physics</p> <blockquote> <p>If the students understands why the physics part of the game engine is hard to get right, then they understand the course. One of my first tasks at the University of Skövde was to take over and run the course Game Physics. This course was offered to the third year game programming students and focused on understanding why physics are hard to get right in games – especially if one take into account the need for performance as well. The course was initially developed by Henrik Engström, who was also the examiner for the course.</p> </blockquote> <p>#Theses</p> <p>#View on Research</p> <p>#View on Pedagogy</p> <p>#Union Commitment</p> <p>#Safety Representative</p> <p>#Personal Life</p> <p>#Finishing Words</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="University of Skövde"/><category term="Work"/><category term="University of Skövde"/><category term="Teaching"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today marks my final workday at the University of Skövde. I have worked here for almost five years, and I believe that a summarization is in order.]]></summary></entry></feed>